there's been a theme at every iPad
announcement for the last few years we
have incredible Hardware but we're
missing the professional quality
software to really put it to use that
has finally changed Apple announced both
Final Cut Pro and also logic pro for the
iPads as long as you have an M1 or newer
I've been editing with Final Cut for the
last few weeks so I'm going to give you
a tour of the interface the usability
what the workflow is like to edit videos
on your iPad we'll talk about the value
of Apple's new subscription model and
I'll let you know as a professional
editor that's been using Final Cut Pro
for years now what do I really think a
Final Cut Pro for the iPad let's take a
look at what Final Cut for iPad does
best and that is quickly sorting through
a lot of footage to make a quick edit so
we're traveling right now which is kind
of a perfect use case for this we are in
Spain and we went to Rwanda the other
day and made a cool little video so I'll
just show you how I'd quickly edit that
if you want to set up your timeline
settings here just so you know automatic
usually really does get it right just
based on whatever the settings of the
first clip that you drop in are so I'm
going to leave it on that for today and
hit continue and as we import a footage
this is one of the things that's going
to limit how I can actually use Final
Cut for iPad and it might be the same
for you it doesn't support external hard
drives at the moment so all of these
clips are in my library which is very
convenient and quick to work with they
synced over iCloud so they're already
here even though I shot them on my
iPhone but the downside is it takes up a
lot of space on your iPad so you're
going to need a very large iPad and even
then it will fill up because these are
creating duplicate copies of the videos
inside of the library as well as in my
photos folder so you just have to be
aware that it could get pretty big and
you'll have to offload them when you're
done editing the interface is very
familiar as a final cut editor on the
Mac it looks similar but it is different
it's clearly optimized for touch and
I'll just show you how I would quickly
go through and edit some of this the
easiest way is that you can do just
click on any of the I should say tap on
any of the clips over here in the
browser and you can just grab these
yellow handles and select the best part
of it and then you could just press hold
and drag it into your timeline that's
kind of the most obvious way I think
that most people would end up adding
things but there are more efficient ways
Apple's put some thought into this so
let's find another nice clip here I
could hit play and then as it goes
through I could set an in point wait
till it's at the end of the good part
and set an out point but there is a more
efficient way to do that there's a jog
wheel which you can activate up here and
then it appears over here on the right
also you can move it around if it's kind
of like getting in your way you can grab
it and move it up and down but this is a
metaphor based off old Hardware that
video editors would use and what I like
about it is that it lets you scrub
through with momentum so you can kind of
throw the footage around if we find a
longer clip here as I go through it's
you know this is a 40 second clip but I
could go from beginning to end in just
one second so I can frame by frame find
the beginning of the movement here
set an out point
then quickly flick through to the end
where does the end there we go and I can
set an out point and now I've got my
markers and instead of clicking and
dragging tapping and dragging which is
always a little slower I'm going to use
the append button here which just drops
it into the end of the timeline this is
the most useful way that I'm usually
adding Clips to the timeline you could
also insert them in between Clips if
that's something you want but what I'm
doing most of the time is appending
another way you could edit is that you
could say select grab a bunch of Clips
append them all into the timeline and
now they're all here everything
including the parts that you don't want
and then you could go through and use
some of these tools Down Below on the
right here these are things I use all
the time on the Mac so I could find the
key moment here and use the blade tool
so that's going to cut between my two
clips and then I can move the playhead
again and these two will trim everything
from the beginning of the playhead then
I'm going to go from this wide shot the
close-up here trim everything from the
beginning and then I think I have
another close-up oh yeah there it is so
I can use the blade tool and zoom in on
what's going on here this one will trim
everything to the right and because the
magnetic timeline as I'm doing this all
the footage is just sucked together it's
very helpful for that so let's say the
magnetic timeline is not behaving the
way you would expect if you for your
example drag a clip away and there is a
gap that is because you have the
position tool on this is helpful this
tool can do a lot of things but the kind
of default behavior is to have it off so
just be aware if that becomes purple
then you might be using an alternate
method of editing I find a lot of people
run into that on the Mac as well and one
more way of editing this is actually
going to be a really useful tool for
anybody that wants to do a bit more of a
pro workflow going from the iPad to the
Mac is that as you select these in and
out points as you go instead of dragging
them into the timeline you can also add
favorites and see how this becomes green
both in the browser and in this preview
of the clip that means that it's been
favorited so I'm going to quickly go
through grab a few random favorite
moments and the power of this favoriting
tool is that it's um useful later so if
you just add things to the timeline it's
kind of hard to go back and find those
clips that you liked to you know sort of
sort them in different ways but as you
can see when we create favorites here
now I'm able to sort them using this
little sorting tool there's various ways
you can sort it by media type or
favorites show favorited and now look we
only have those moments it's just the
part of the clip that we asked for so
I'm going to clear out my whole timeline
here just delete everything I've done
grab all of these clips
append and now I almost have like a
little edited video because since it's
only the good parts as it plays back
it'll almost be slightly edited then all
you have to do later is sort of trim
them tighten them up but that metadata
is retained As you move the project onto
the max you could have one editor
selecting your favorites and then
another editor doing the final edit on
the Mac with the iPad being so portable
I think one of the biggest advantages
will be this sort of quick and dirty
type of edit when you're like on the go
I made a little either Instagram reel or
Tick Tock a vertical video that can show
you as an example I think this is going
to be something it's very strong for so
this was kind of a perfect editing
scenario for traveling because my iPad
is a small device I can carry it with me
and it already had all of the footage
from my iPhone that I'd been shooting
since it synced over iCloud so I didn't
even have to airdrop or transfer it
anyway it was just already available
only took a few minutes to put this
together and as you can see it's using
that Dynamic music which I hope this
feature starts getting a larger library
but as you stretch it the music just
becomes the length that you want it to
be I mean this can be 10 minutes long if
you want I would love for other
third-party developers to be able to add
music to this I know it's possible so
please Apple they did say that more
effects will be coming soon from third
parties so I can't wait to see that
there's some good ones in here but I
think we could especially see more from
motion VFX I use those all the time on
the Mac one really cool new effect is
scene removal mask and I was hoping to
do it on this clip so that she would be
over top of the title unfortunately you
just have to be aware that it needs to
be used on a clip where there's no
Motion in it so the background should
stay static where just the subject is
moving I don't have an example of that
I'm moving all the time and all my Clips
so I wasn't really able to test that one
so all these things are what I think
Final Cut does great on the iPad here's
a few that it falls a bit flat so this
is footage from either my traditional
bigger cameras that I'd use in the
YouTube videos or drones and when I say
flat let me show you what I mean so I've
selected this clip I'm going to open up
the inspector and over here there are
some basic Lut tools so I can say that
this was shot in Canon log 2. if I turn
that off you can see it's a completely
flat image like there's you know no
saturation no contrast in it if I turn
on log processing it does know that this
is Canon okay right so there's contrast
here this this doesn't look good this is
not how I would typically color grade my
footage basically all professional
cameras are going to be shooting in log
so the lack of proper log support is
unfortunate it does mean there's going
to be some limitations of the type of
footage I can work with on the iPad if
you are going to be doing color grading
you're going to be needing to look at
something like DaVinci Resolve which has
all of its color Tools in here which is
actually insane that they were able to
do so much but it's act it's editor like
the way you cut footage together in
resolve I really I don't I don't like it
I mean I find it much much stronger over
in Final Cut Pro so this is what I'd use
for editing whereas resolve has those
color grading tools oh and while I'm
talking about things I miss from the Mac
one other one if I drop this drone shot
in here is I really wish it had all of
the speed ramping tools that the Mac has
so in my inspector over here I am able
to just turn up the speed of that clip
but on the Mac I was able to add speed
ramping so I'd be like okay this first
part I want to be really quick and then
I want to slow down gradually here I
could cut it and then instantly it slows
down and speeds up but it's just not
nearly as elegant as the way that it
happens on the Mac so this has always
been an advantage of Final Cut over the
other editors let me play it back for
you here but now it is just kind of more
similar to what you're seeing on other
software I didn't do a great job there
but that's what I'm saying speed ramping
I hope they match the features that are
available on the Mac for that and
obviously another big difference from
the Mac is that it is now subscription
when you are using a final cut for iPad
I don't love subscriptions and not ideal
but the pricing is pretty reasonable
five dollars a month or 49 a year so for
example I paid 300 for Final Cut Pro for
the Mac it would take about six years to
pay that much here I really hope this
means that more support is coming for
Final Cut That updates will happen often
because for example with Adobe if you
just want Premiere you're spending
twenty dollars a month that's four times
as much but you're getting updates all
the time Adobe has been really
aggressive with their updates for
reference though you can get a free copy
of resolve so that's where Final Cut
sits basically in the middle uh Adobe
products are much more expensive Final
Cuts a lower priced subscription and
resolve starts off free and then you can
also do a one-time payment to own it so
let's take a look at a more complete
edit here back to our day trip to Ronda
one feature I love because I used to try
to do this on the Mac and there was no
easy way so I'd actually do screen
recordings in my iPad then put it over
top and that's live drawing so here I'll
delete this one I did before show you
again unfortunately I don't have great
handwriting so you're just gonna have to
bear with me if I had an apple pencil
with me I'm sure it would look a little
bit better but I'm just going to do my
best here what it would really be useful
for is actually arrows like pointing at
things or highlighting features on the
screen I'm going to use it for that all
the time and as it plays back you can
also change the speed so let's see
oh that fits actually perfectly inside
of that clip but uh in other examples it
may not you can open the inspector and
over here say how long do I want it to
take to draw so I could have it be much
much quicker let's say and then just
takes a moment for it to appear on
screen all this footage that I'm
scrubbing through by the way this is 4K
footage running on an M2 iPad Pro
playback is perfectly smooth and it's at
higher quality you can set that quality
by the way so right now it's playing at
high quality you can also have
performance if it was slowing down a
little bit it also supports video scopes
just like you're used to on the Mac the
waveforms and vectorscope all the things
that you may need for color grading
hopefully better color tools come at
some point by the way let's actually
look at those just really quickly if I
pick a clip and do any of these need it
so if I want to actually modify these
colors let's look at what those are I
can open up the inspector here add
effects and I'm going to use color
adjustments now at first glance it seems
like there's a lot of power in here and
turn off the browser so I can see this
bigger unfortunately the footage just
doesn't respond in the way I'd want it
to like moving the exposure it instantly
Clips it doesn't seem to understand that
exposure is mostly about the mid-tones
brightness has a bit more of that effect
but it also has a weird response on the
kind of saturation in the shadows this
is not a great color grading tool I
would expect more power out of it than
this of course there's more tools than I
had time to get to in here a lot going
on and eventually I'll get to all of it
I still have to understand some of them
myself but there's also things like
multi-cam support I didn't have any
multicam footage to work with on this
example the volume is always available
so you can turn your Clips up and down
remember to close it sometimes I'd find
that the behavior wasn't as expected but
it's because I left my volume panel open
over here in options you can change the
appearance of the timeline like clip
height this is kind of important to play
with your audio meters can be turned on
and off which are visible on the right
snapping I generally have this on so the
clips click together and that is your
Whirlwind tour of Final Cut Pro for iPad
I've been a final cut editor for years
now starting with seven and then I was
at the announcement of Final Cut Pro 10
at nav back in 2011 and I've loved it it
is a fantastic workflow I use it for our
professional work and for YouTube it's
extremely fast and thoughtfully designed
and it's hard for me when I switch over
to either resolve or Premiere because
Apple had a real breakthrough with the
magnetic timeline and I just I prefer it
over everything else Final Cut Pro for
iPad is missing some big things things
that are important to me and just my
daily workflow they're not even that
advanced like file management all you
can do is keep all of your Clips inside
the library on the iPad and you can move
that library to a Mac to do further
editing it doesn't go backwards you
can't bring it from the Mac to the iPad
but a real limitation is that you're not
using any external storage meaning all
the files have to be on an iPad so I
know that Apple's doing this for ease of
use it's much easier for a beginner user
to understand but it means that my iPad
is going to fill up quickly so you're
going to need a really big one and even
if it's big you're going to have to be
moving files on and off of it somehow
I'm not sure how they would expect file
management to work if you edited a lot
on the iPad probably my other biggest
disappointment is the lack of color
management in general of course this can
come in the future basic things like Lut
support which is available in other
editors like cap cut or lumafusion and
this is a problem because whenever
record on bigger cameras like this is
the Lumix s52x I record in log so the
image is completely flat and needs a lot
added to it to even be usable and I
don't plan to switch away from not using
logs so to me what I'd be editing the
most often on an iPad is iPhone footage
which is the thing that's what I was
doing today it looked great but it's a
more limited use case than when I'm on
the Mac but you know what overall I
think Apple has done some amazing things
here this is the best video editing
interface I've used on an iPad I've
tried to get used to Fusion it has every
feature you want I know people do real
jobs using it but the interface is
horrifying it does not look nice it
doesn't feel good to be in there it's
very clunky and hard to get used to
other apps like resolve which they did
an amazing job of bringing almost like
the full app onto the iPad but it's
almost a one-to-one transfer of resolve
from the desktop I really like that
Apple thought through the touch
interfaces how would you want to
experience an app on the iPad and it
shows it is much more intuitive than any
of those other editors so if you don't
have a lot of files to manage you're not
doing extensive color grading you don't
need big effects Final Cut Pro is the
best editor for iPad
[Music]
Network
Sports
oh